Guide to the Hamilton Aïdé Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Hamilton Aïdé papers
1824-1906
GEN MSS 207
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.65
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence to, from, and about Aïdé; his diary for a trip to Switzerland in the second half of 1870, a scrapbook of reviews of his work, and miscellaneous poetry and prose pieces. The correspondence is both personal and business oriented, including letters from publishers, editors and friends regarding the publicaton of novels and songs. Principal correspondents include Matthew Arnold, Frances Hodgson Burnett,James Anthony Froude, William Money Hardinge, Henry James, Fanny Kemble, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, and William Stirling Maxwell.
Aïdé, Hamilton, 1826-1906
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased with the Morton Fullerton Papers, 1970.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Fullerton Papers are now housed in the Yale Collection of American Literature.
Scope and Contents
The Hamilton Aïdé papers have been divided into four series:
Series I: MATERIAL BY AIDÉ: includes his diary and letters by Aïdé. Letters from Aïdé to Morton Fullerton are with the Fullerton Papers.
Series II: LETTERS TO AIDÉ: comprises the greatest part of the collection. Cards have been made for the most important correspondents. Letters from Morton Fullerton to Aïdé are in the Fullerton Papers.
Series III: LETTERS ABOUT AIDÉ: consists primarily of letters from Sir William Stirling-Maxwell to Mrs. Martin.
Series IV: MISCELLANEA
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Composers -- England -- Correspondence; Switzerland -- Description and travel; Diaries; Aïdé, Hamilton, 1826-1906; Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888; Bispham, David, 1857-1921; Blowitz, A. Opper de (Adolphe Opper), 1825-1903; Burnett, Frances Hodgson, 1849-1924; Cobbe, Frances Power, 1822-1904; Courthope, William John, 1842-1917; Field, Roswell Martin, 1851-1919; Frohman, Daniel, 1851-1940; Froude, James Anthony, 1818-1894; Garrett, Edmund H. (Edmund Henry), 1853-1929; Hardinge, William Money, 1855-; Hovey, Richard, 1864-1900; Huddleston, Diana De Vere, Lady, d. 1905; James, Henry, 1843-1916; Kemble, Fanny, 1809-1893; Kendal, William Hunter, 1843-1917; Knowles, James, Sir, 1831-1908; Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, Earl of, 1831-1891; Mallock, W. H. (William Hurrell), 1849-1923; Merivale, Herman Charles, 1839-1906; Myers, Eveleen Tennant; Ritchie, Anne Thackeray, 1837-1919; Russell, Mary Agatha, 1853-1933; Stirling Maxwell, William, 1818-1878; Wantage, Robert James Loyd-Lindsay, Baron, 1832-1901; Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith, 1856-1923
- Material by Hamilton Aïdé, 1870 Jul-Dec; Series I
  - Diary, 1870 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    No place
  - 2 ALS to Georgina (Collier) Aïdé (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - No place, n.d.
    - No place, n.y. Apr 11
  - 8 ALS to Harriet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - South sea, n.y. Apr 10
    - London, n.y. May 1
    - South sea, n.y. Sep 25
    - Beaurivage, n.y. Sep 29
    - Lennon Love, n.d.
    - Paris, n.d.
    - Ripple Court, n.d.
    - No place, n.d.
  - ALS to unidentified recipient (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Scarborough, n.d.
  - ALS to unidentified recipient (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Piltown, n.d.
- Letters to Hamilton Aïdé, Series II
  - Allonville, S. d' (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Farnboro, Hants., n.d.
  - Amory, Carl S. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bedford, 1824 Oct 6
  - Arnold, Matthew (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - London, n.y. Jul 9
    - London, n.y. Jul 9
    - London, n.y. Jun 21
  - Barwell, Fred B. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - London, 1861 Dec 7
  - Bispham, David Scull (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - London
  - Blanc, Charles (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mendon, n.y. Jul 8
    - Paris, n.y. Mar 10
  - Blanc, Edouard (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Paris, 1897 Oct 18
  - Blowitz, Henry Georges Stéphane Adolphe de (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Paris, 1894 Oct 10
  - Boyle, Eleanor Nevel (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Summerhill, Aberdeenshire, n.y. Oct 17
  - Bradly, P W (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - London, 1906 Oct 13
  - Burnett, Frances Hodgson (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Near Maidstone, n.d.
  - Cobbe, Frances Power (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Dolgelly, North Wales, n.y. Mar 3
  - Courthorpe, William John (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - London, 1886 Jul 30
  - Dawnay, Henry D. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Paris, 1898 Feb 12
  - Field, Roswell Martin (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Boston, 1875 Jul 7
  - Fisher, Cecil Edward (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bournemouth, 1901 Oct 18
  - Florence, G. de Clermont, Countess (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - London, 189-
  - Frohman, Daniel (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - London, n.y. May 22
    - London, n.y. May 28
  - Froude, James Anthony (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - London, n.y. Mar 3
    - London, n.y. May 1
    - London, n.y. May 4
    - London, n.y. May 5
    - London, n.y. Jun 28
  - Garrett, Edmund Henry (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Winchester, Mass., 1894 Dec 7
  - Genestory, Calemard de (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Paris, 1902 Mar 22
  - Hardinge, William M (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Various places, 16 letters, no dates
  - Hovey, Richard (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - No place, n.d.
  - Huddlestone, Diana De Vere, lady, d' (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Bournemouth, n.d.
    - Bournemouth, 1891 Oct 21
  - James, Henry (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rye, 1898 Jun 30
  - James R. Osgood & Co. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Boston, 1873 Apr 24
  - Jessup, Augustus E (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Glanis, 1897 Sep 9
    - Shaftsbury, Dorset, 1905 Mar 5
  - Jessup, Hyacinth (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - London, 1906 Jun 2
    - Aargau, Switzerland, 1906 Jun 26
  - Kemble, Frances Anne (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - No place, n.d.
    - Monte d'Orta, n.y. Aug 7
  - Kendal, William Hunter (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - London, 1896 Feb 6
    - London, 1896 Mar 1
  - Knowles, Sir James Thomas (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - London, 1891 Jul 17
  - Leopold, prince, duke of Albany (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Balmoral, n.d.
  - Lonsdale, Robert E (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - London, 1867 Jun 4
  - Lowth, G T (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Ascot, n.y. Feb 18
  - Lucas, Reginald Jaffray (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - London, 1906 Dec 8
  - Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer-Lytton, 1st earl of (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Simla, 1880 May 13
  - Lytton, Robert (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - The Hague, 1856 Dec 24
  - Mallock, William Hurrell (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Bryansford, 1896 Aug 26
  - Merivale, Herman Charles (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Kingston on Thames, 1880 Mar 12
  - Myers, Eveleen (Tennant) (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Cambridge, 1903 Nov 7
    - Cumberland, 1904 Sep 25
  - Navarro, Mary Anderson de (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Divonne, France, n.d.
  - Parry, Clinton (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Gronville, Jersey, 1879 Mar 29
  - Ritchie, Anne Isabella (Thackeray), lady (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - London
  - Routledge, E (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - London, 1882 Apr 5
  - Russell, Mary Agatha (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Richmond, Surrey, 1884 Apr 14
  - Scott, Charles N (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - No place, n.d.
  - Shelley (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Bournemouth, 1904 Jan 1
  - Sichel, Walter (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - London, 1888 Jul 17
  - Slaughter Colegrove & Co. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - London, 1896 Mar 26
  - Standish, Hélène (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Paris, 1888 May 13
  - Swan Sonnenschein & Co. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - London, 1889 Jan 9
  - Tajolius [?] Maria (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - No place, 1905 Oct 12
  - Tharf, Gerald (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - London, n.y. Jul 20
  - Thours, Harold (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Haslemere, Surrey, 1906 Nov 25
  - Tillotson's Newspaper Literature (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Bolton, Lancashire, 1891 Jun 22
  - Vison [?] Edward (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - London, 1884 Jan 21
    - London, 1893 Jul 20
    - S. Devon, 1893 Aug 15
    - S. Devon, 1893 Aug 17
  - Wantage, Robert James Lloyd-Lindsay, 1st baron (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - London, n.y. Jun 23
  - Wiggin, Kate Douglas (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - London, 1901 Jun 16
  - Wister, Sarah Butler (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Philadelphia, 1905 Feb 11
  - Womrast, Kay (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Pelham Heights, N.Y., n.d.
  - Unidentified Correspondents (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - signed Teresa Cao d'Ail, n.y. Dec 3
    - signed "L" Cracovie, 1902 Aug 20
    - signed "L" Cracovie, 1902 Oct 4
    - unsigned fragment Oxford, n.d.
    - signature illegible No place, 1902 Nov 7
    - unsigned fragment (French) No place, n.d.
    - signed "S.D." Isle of Wight, n.y. Oct 6
- Letters about Hamilton Aïdé, 1898 Feb 26; Series III
  - Henry Graves & Co., 1898 Feb 26 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    London AL (signed with a stamp) to Col. Clarence Collier
  - Stirling-Maxwell, Sir William, Bart., 1818-78 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    14 ALS to Mrs. Martin
    - London, 1848 Jan 2
    - Keir, 1848 Oct 24
    - London, 1850 Oct 23
    - Keir, 1850 Oct 27
    - London, 1872 Mar 29
    - London, 1872 May 11
    - Keir, 1874 Feb 16
    - Brighton, 1875 Sep 28
    - London, n.y. Jan 24
    - London, n.y. Feb 19
    - London, n.y. Jun 21
    - London, n.y. Jul 27
    - London, n.y. May 3
    - London, n.y. Dec 1
  - Unidentified correspondent, 1902 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Copent ALS (illegible signature) to Baring
  - Unidentified correspondent, n.y. Jul 31 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    Carnot ALS (illegible signature) to Col. Clarence Collier In French
  - Unidentified correspondent, 1859? Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    Cragdon ALS (illegible signature) to Miss Gordon
- MISCELLANEA, Series IV
  - Aïdé, Hamilton (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Scrapbook: reviews of Aïdés work, 1858-83
  - Aïdá, George (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Deposition concerning a duel fought, 1828
    - by M. Aida in 1828 Paris
  - Miscellaneous poetry and prose pieces found in the papers of Hamilton Aïdé (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Memorandum: unsigned (Box 2, Folder 75)
    no place
  - Envelope, with the notation: Letter and rough draught of reply. (Box 2, Folder 76)